There are times when I feel really quite ashamed
هنالك أوقات أشعر فيها حقيقةً بالخجل
to be a European.
كوني أوروبياً.
In the last year,
في العام الماضي،
more than a million people arrived in Europe in need of our help,
وصل أكثر من مليون شخص إلى أوروبا في حاجة إلى مساعدتنا،
and our response, frankly, has been pathetic.
وكان ردنا، بصراحة، مثيراً للشفقة.
There are just so many contradictions.
هناك الكثير من المتناقضات ،
We mourn the tragic death
فقد حزنا بشدة على الوفاة المأساوية
of two-year-old Alan Kurdi,
للطفل الكردي ذي العامين ،
and yet, since then, more than 200 children
و منذ ذلك الحين، غرق أكثرمن 200 طفل
have subsequently drowned in the Mediterranean.
في وقت لاحق في البحر الأبيض المتوسط.
We have international treaties
لدينا معاهدات دولية
that recognize that refugees are a shared responsibility,
تقر أن اللاجئين هي مسؤولية مشتركة،
and yet we accept that tiny Lebanon
ولكننا قبلنا أن لبنان الصغير
hosts more Syrians than the whole of Europe combined.
يستضيف سوريين أكثر من من أوروبا كلها.
We lament the existence of human smugglers,
نحن نأسف لوجود مهربين للبشر ،
and yet we make that the only viable route
ولكنا جعلناها الطريق الوحيد القابل للتطبيق
to seek asylum in Europe.
لطلب اللجوء في أوروبا.
We have labor shortages,
لدينا نقص في العمالة،
and yet we exclude people who fit our economic and demographic needs
ولكننا استثنينا هؤلاء الناس الذين تنطبق عليهم احتياجاتنا الاقتصادية والديموغرافية
from coming to Europe.
من القدوم إلى أوروبا.
We proclaim our liberal values in opposition to fundamentalist Islam,
نحن نصرح بالقيم الليبرالية التي لدينا في معارضة الإسلام المتعصب ،
and yet --
ولكن --
we have repressive policies
لدينا سياسات قمعية
that detain child asylum seekers,
تعيق طالبي اللجوء الأطفال،
that separate children from their families,
وتفرق بين الأطفال وأسرهم ،
and that seize property from refugees.
وتحتجز ممتلكات اللاجئين .
What are we doing?
ماذا نفعل؟
How has the situation come to this,
كيف وصل الوضع إلى هذا الحد ،
that we've adopted such an inhumane response to a humanitarian crisis?
بأن نتبنى هذه السياسة غيرالإنسانية لمواجهة هذه الأزمة الإنسانية ؟
I don't believe it's because people don't care,
لا أعتقد أن سبب هذا هو أن الناس لا يهتمون ،
or at least I don't want to believe it's because people don't care.
أو على الأقل أنا لا أريد أن أصدق ذلك .
I believe it's because our politicians lack a vision,
ولكني أعتقد أن سبب ذلك هو أن ساستنا يفتقرون إلى الرؤية ،
a vision for how to adapt an international refugee system
رؤية لكيفية تَبْنِي نظام دولي للاجئين
created over 50 years ago
تم إنشاؤه قبل أكثر من 50 عاماً
for a changing and globalized world.
للعالم المتغير والمعولم .
And so what I want to do is take a step back
ولذلك ما أريد القيام به هو اتخاذ خطوة إلى الوراء
and ask two really fundamental questions,
وأسأل سؤالين جوهريين ،
the two questions we all need to ask.
نحن جميعا بحاجة إلى أن نسأل السؤالين ،
First, why is the current system not working?
السؤال الأول ، لماذا لا يعمل النظام الحالي ؟
And second, what can we do to fix it?
وثانياً، ما الذي يمكننا القيام به لإصلاح هذا النظام ؟
So the modern refugee regime
إن نظام اللاجئين الحديث
was created in the aftermath of the Second World War by these guys.
تم إنشاؤه في أعقاب الحرب العالمية الثانية من قبل هؤلاء الرجال.
Its basic aim is to ensure
وهدفها الأساسي هو ضمان
that when a state fails, or worse, turns against its own people,
أنه عندما تخفق الدولة،أو يحدث ما هو أسوأ، بأن يتحول النظام ضد شعبه ،
people have somewhere to go,
يجد الناس مكاناً للذهاب إليه ،
to live in safety and dignity until they can go home.
ليعيشوا بأمن وكرامة حتى يتسنى لهم الرجوع لوطنهم .
It was created precisely for situations like the situation we see in Syria today.
لقد أنشئت على وجه التحديد لحالات مثل الوضع الذي نراه في سوريا اليوم،
Through an international convention signed by 147 governments,
من خلال اتفاقية دولية وقعت من قبل 147حكومة ،
the 1951 Convention on the Status of Refugees,
وهي اتفاقية عام 1951 حول وضع اللاجئين،
and an international organization, UNHCR,
والمفوضية الدولية ،
states committed to reciprocally admit people onto their territory
حددت أنه يجب على الدول المعاملة بالمثل للناس المتواجدين على أراضيها
who flee conflict and persecution.
الذين يفرون من الصراع والاضطهاد.
But today, that system is failing.
ولكن اليوم، هذا النظام فشل .
In theory, refugees have a right to seek asylum.
فمن الناحية النظرية، فإن للاجئين الحق في طلب اللجوء.
In practice, our immigration policies block the path to safety.
ولكن من الناحية العملية، سياسات الهجرة لدينا قائمة على قطع الطريق إلى بر الأمان.
In theory, refugees have a right to a pathway to integration,
من الناحية النظرية، يحق للاجيء أن يتم دمجه في المجتمع ،
or return to the country they've come from.
أو أن يتم إعادته إلى البلد التي جاء منها ،
But in practice, they get stuck in almost indefinite limbo.
ولكن في الواقع يبقى مصيرهم طي النسيان إلى أجل غير مسمى .
In theory, refugees are a shared global responsibility.
من الناحية النظرية، قضية اللاجئين هي مسؤولية عالمية مشتركة.
In practice, geography means that countries proximate the conflict
ولكن من الناحية العملية ،الجغرافيا تعني بأن الدول القريبة من الصراع
take the overwhelming majority of the world's refugees.
تأخذ الأغلبية الساحقة من اللاجئين في العالم.
The system isn't broken because the rules are wrong.
لم يتم كسر هذا النظام لأن قواعده خاطئة.
It's that we're not applying them adequately to a changing world,
فلم نقم بتطبيقه على نحو كاف في هذا العالم المتغير،
and that's what we need to reconsider.
وهذا ما نحن بحاجة إعادة النظر فيه .
So I want to explain to you a little bit about how the current system works.
لذلك أريد أن أشرح لكم قليلاً عن الكيفية التي يعمل بها النظام الحالي.
How does the refugee regime actually work?
وكيف يعمل نظام اللاجئين فعلياً ؟
But not from a top-down institutional perspective,
ولكن ليس من الأعلى إلى الأسفل من ناحية المنظور المؤسسي،
rather from the perspective of a refugee.
بدلاً من وجهة نظر اللاجئين.
So imagine a Syrian woman.
لذا تخيل إمراة سورية ،
Let's call her Amira.
ودعنا نسميها أميرة ،
And Amira to me represents many of the people I've met in the region.
وأميرة بالنسبة لي تمثل الكثير من الناس الذين التقيت بهم في المنطقة.
Amira, like around 25 percent of the world's refugees,
أميرة، تمثل حوالي 25 في المئة من اللاجئين في العالم،
is a woman with children,
وهي امرأة لديها أطفال،
and she can't go home because she comes from this city
ولا تستطيع العودة إلى ديارهم لأنها أتت من هذه المدينة
that you see before you, Homs,
الذي ترونها أمامكم، وهي حمص،
a once beautiful and historic city
المدينة التي كانت يوماً ما جميلة وتاريخية
now under rubble.
والآن تحت الانقاض.
And so Amira can't go back there.
و هكذا فإن أميرة لا يمكن لها أن تذهب إلى هناك.
But Amira also has no hope of resettlement to a third country,
كما أنه ليس لديها أي أمل لإعادة التوطين في بلد ثالث،
because that's a lottery ticket
لأن ذلك كتذكرة اليانصيب
only available to less than one percent of the world's refugees.
متاح فقط إلى أقل من واحد في المئة من اللاجئين في العالم.
So Amira and her family
لذلك فإن أميرة وعائلتها
face an almost impossible choice.
تواجه خياراً شبه مستحيل.
They have three basic options.
لديهم ثلاثة خيارات أساسية.
The first option is that Amira can take her family to a camp.
الخيار الأول هو أن بإمكان أميرة أخذ عائلتها إلى المخيم ،
In the camp, she might get assistance,
الذي من الممكن أن تحصل فيه على المساعدة ،
but there are very few prospects for Amira and her family.
ولكن هناك عدد قليل جداً من التوقعات أمام أميرة وأسرتها.
Camps are in bleak, arid locations,
فالمخيمات في أماكن قاتمة، وقاحلة،
often in the desert.
وغالباً ما تكون في الصحراء .
In the Zaatari refugee camp in Jordan,
ففي مخيم الزعتري في الأردن،
you can hear the shells across the border in Syria at nighttime.
يمكنك سماع صوت القذائف ليلاً عبر الحدود في سوريا .
There's restricted economic activity.
هناك نشاط اقتصادي مقيد.
Education is often of poor quality.
,التعليم هو في كثير من الأحيان من نوعية رديئة.
And around the world,
وحول العالم،
some 80 percent of refugees who are in camps
نحو 80 في المئة من اللاجئين الذين يعيشون في مخيمات
have to stay for at least five years.
يجب عليهم أن يبقوا فيها لمدة خمس سنوات على الأقل.
It's a miserable existence,
انها حياة بائسة،
and that's probably why, in reality,
وربما كان هذا السبب، في الواقع،
only nine percent of Syrians choose that option.
بأن تسعة في المئة فقط من السوريين لجأوا الى هذا الخيار.
Alternatively, Amira can head to an urban area
وبدلا من ذلك، بإمكان أميرة الذهاب إلى المناطق الحضرية
in a neighboring country, like Amman or Beirut.
الى مدن مجاور، مثل عمان أو بيروت.
That's an option that about 75 percent of Syrian refugees have taken.
وهذا الخيار اتخذه حوالي 75 في المئة من االلاجئين السوريين .
But there, there's great difficulty as well.
ولكن هنالك، صعوبة كبيرة كذلك ،
Refugees in such urban areas don't usually have the right to work.
فااللاجئين في هذه المناطق الحضرية ليس لديهم في الغالب الحق في العمل ،
They don't usually get significant access to assistance.
ولا يتسيطيعون عادةً الوصول الى المساعدات ،
And so when Amira and her family have used up their basic savings,
ولذلك عندما استخدمت أميرة وعائلتها مدخراتهم الأساسية ،
they're left with very little and likely to face urban destitution.
فإنه من المرجح أن يواجههم الفقر في المناطق الحضرية .
So there's a third alternative,
لذلك فإن هناك بديل ثالث لهم ،
and it's one that increasing numbers of Syrians are taking.
وهذا السبب الذي زاد أعداد اللاجئين لدينا
Amira can seek some hope for her family
حيث يمكن لأميرة التماس بعض الأمل لعائلتها
by risking their lives on a dangerous and perilous journey
بالمخاطرة بحياتهم في رحلة محفوفة بالمخاطر
to another country,
إلى دولة أخرى،
and it's that which we're seeing in Europe today.
وهذا ما نشهده في أوروبا اليوم.
Around the world, we present refugees with an almost impossible choice
فحول العالم ،نحن نواجه لاجئين في الغالب ليس لديهم خيار آخر
between three options:
بين الخيارات الثلاثة
encampment, urban destitution and dangerous journeys.
وهي المخيم أو الفقر في المناطق الحضرية المجاورة أو رحلة محفوفة بالمخاطر .
For refugees, that choice is the global refugee regime today.
وبالنسبة للاجئين، فأن هذا الخيار هونظام اللاجئين العالمي اليوم.
But I think it's a false choice.
ولكن اعتقد انه خيار خاطيء.
I think we can reconsider that choice.
وأنه يمكن لنا أن نعيد النظر في هذا الاختيار.
The reason why we limit those options
والسبب وراء تقليص هذه الخيارات
is because we think
راجع الى أننا نعتقد
that those are the only options that are available to refugees,
أن تلك هي الخيارات الوحيدة التي تتوفر للاجئين،
and they're not.
ولا يوجد خيارات سواها .
Politicians frame the issue as a zero-sum issue,
السياسيون قاموا بتأطير القضية كقضية محصلتها صفر،
that if we benefit refugees, we're imposing costs on citizens.
بحيث أنه لو استفدنا من اللاجئين فاننا سنفرض تكاليف على المواطنين .
We tend to have a collective assumption
نحن نميل الى افتراض جماعي
that refugees are an inevitable cost or burden to society.
بأن اللاجئين هم تكلفة لا مفر منها أو عبئا على المجتمع.
But they don't have to. They can contribute.
ولكن هذا ليس بالضرورة ويمكنهم أن يسهموا في المجمتع ،
So what I want to argue
و ما أود طرحه
is there are ways in which we can expand that choice set
هو أنه بإمكاننا أن نوسع تلك الخيارات
and still benefit everyone else:
بحيث يستفيد منها الجميع :
the host states and communities,
الدول المضيفة والمجتمعات،
our societies and refugees themselves.
مجتمعاتنا واللاجئين أنفسهم.
And I want to suggest four ways
لذا أود أن أقترح أربع طرق
we can transform the paradigm of how we think about refugees.
يمكننا من خلالها تغير طريقة تفكيرنا بقضية اللاجئين .
All four ways have one thing in common:
وكل هذه الطرق الأربع لديها قاسم مشترك :
they're all ways in which we take the opportunities of globalization,
وهي أنها هي الطرق ذاتها التي توصلنا الى العولمة ،
mobility and markets,
التنقل والأسواق،
and update the way we think about the refugee issue.
وتحديث الطريقة التي نفكر بها حول قضية اللاجئين.
The first one I want to think about
أول طريقة أود التفكير بها
is the idea of enabling environments,
هي فكرة البيئات التمكينية،
and it starts from a very basic recognition
التي تبدأ من اعتراف أساسسي
that refugees are human beings like everyone else,
أن اللاجئين هم بشر مثل أي شخص آخر،
but they're just in extraordinary circumstances.
ولكنهم فقط في ظروف استثنائية.
Together with my colleagues in Oxford,
جنبا إلى جنب مع زملائي في أكسفورد،
we've embarked on a research project in Uganda
شرعت في مشروع بحثي في أوغندا
looking at the economic lives of refugees.
عن الحياة الاقتصادية للاجئين.
We chose Uganda not because it's representative of all host countries.
وقد اخترنا أوغندا ليس لأنها ممثلة لجميع البلدان المضيفة.
It's not. It's exceptional.
ليس كذلك. بل لإنها استثنائية.
Unlike most host countries around the world,
وخلافاً لمعظم البلدان المضيفة حول العالم،
what Uganda has done
ما قامت به أوغندا
is give refugees economic opportunity.
هو إعطاء اللاجئين الفرص الاقتصادية ،
It gives them the right to work. It gives them freedom of movement.
لقد أعطتهم الحق في العمل وحرية التنقل ،
And the results of that are extraordinary
والنتائج المترتبة على ذلك هي غير عادية
both for refugees and the host community.
على كل من اللاجئين والمجتمعات المضيفة.
In the capital city, Kampala,
في العاصمة كمبالا،
we found that 21 percent of refugees own a business that employs other people,
وجدنا أن 21 في المئة من اللاجئين يملكون الأعمال التجارية التي توظف أشخاص آخرين،
and 40 percent of those employees
و 40 في المئة من هؤلاء الموظفين
are nationals of the host country.
من مواطني البلد المضيف.
In other words, refugees are making jobs
وبعبارة أخرى، فإن اللاجئين يخلقون وظائف
for citizens of the host country.
للمواطنين في البلد المضيف.
Even in the camps, we found extraordinary examples
حتى في المخيمات، وجدنا أمثلة استثنائية
of vibrant, flourishing and entrepreneurial businesses.
لشركات ريادية مزدهرة و نابضة بالحياة ،
For example, in a settlement called Nakivale,
على سبيل المثال، في مستوطنة تدعى ناكيفال،
we found examples of Congolese refugees
وجدنا أمثلة من اللاجئين الكونغوليين
running digital music exchange businesses.
يديرون شركات موسيقية رقمية .
We found a Rwandan who runs a business that's available
وجدنا روانديين الذي يدير الأعمال التجارية المتوفرة
to allow the youth to play computer games
التي تتيح للشباب لعب ألعاب الكمبيوتر
on recycled games consoles and recycled televisions.
من تلفزيونات وألعاب معاد تدويرها ،
Against the odds of extreme constraint,
على خلاف القيود التي تفرض عليهم في أماكن أخرى ،
refugees are innovating,
فإن اللاجئين يبتكرون ،
and the gentleman you see before you is a Congolese guy called Demou-Kay.
والرجل الذي ترونه أمامكم هو كونغولي يدعى ديمو-كاي.
Demou-Kay arrived in the settlement with very little,
وصل ديمو-كاي الى هذه المستوطنة مع القليل جدا،
but he wanted to be a filmmaker.
لكنه أراد ان يكون مخرجاً .
So with friends and colleagues, he started a community radio station,
فبدأ بمحطة إذاعة محلية، مع مجموعة من الأصدقاء والزملاء ،
he rented a video camera,
استأجر كاميرا فيديو،
and he's now making films.
وهو الآن صانع أفلام ،
He made two documentary films
وقدم فيلمين وثائقيين
with and for our team,
مع فريقنا،
and he's making a successful business out of very little.
ونجح في إقامة مشروع تجاري من القليل جدا.
It's those kinds of examples
انها تلك الأنواع من الأمثلة
that should guide our response to refugees.
التي ينبغي أن توجه ردنا على اللاجئين.
Rather than seeing refugees
بدلا من رؤية اللاجئين
as inevitably dependent upon humanitarian assistance,
على أنهم يعتمدوا بشكل حتمي على المساعدة الإنسانية،
we need to provide them with opportunities for human flourishing.
نحن بحاجة إلى توفير فرص لهم تسعى إلى ازدهار الإنسان.
Yes, clothes, blankets, shelter, food
نعم، الملابس والبطانيات والمأوى والغذاء
are all important in the emergency phase,
كلها مهمة في مرحلة الطوارئ،
but we need to also look beyond that.
ولكن علينا أيضاً أن ننظر إلى أبعد من ذلك.
We need to provide opportunities to connectivity, electricity,
نحن بحاجة إلى توفير فرص إلى الاتصال والكهرباء،
education, the right to work,
التعليم، والحق في العمل،
access to capital and banking.
الحصول على رأس المال والخدمات المصرفية.
All the ways in which we take for granted
كل الطرق التي نتخذها
that we are plugged in to the global economy
للوصول الى الاقتصاد العالمي
can and should apply to refugees.
يمكن ويجب أن تنطبق على اللاجئين.
The second idea I want to discuss is economic zones.
أما الفكرة الثانية التي أريد أن أتحدث عنها فهي المناطق الاقتصادية.
Unfortunately, not every host country in the world
لسوء الحظ، ليس كل الدول المضيفة بالعالم
takes the approach Uganda has taken.
مارست نفس الطرق التي اتخذتها أوعندا ،
Most host countries don't open up their economies to refugees
معظم البلدان المضيفة لا تفتح اقتصاداتها للاجئين
in the same way.
بنفس الطريقة.
But there are still pragmatic alternative options that we can use.
ولكن لا تزال هناك خيارات واقعية بديلة يمكن أن نستخدمها.
Last April, I traveled to Jordan with my colleague,
في شهر أبريل الماضي، سافرت إلى الأردن مع زميلي ،
the development economist Paul Collier,
برفقة اقتصادي التنمية بول كولير،
and we brainstormed an idea while we were there
وخطرت في بالنا فكرة بينما كنا هناك
with the international community and the government,
مع المجتمع الدولي والحكومة،
an idea to bring jobs to Syrians
فكرة لتقديم فرص العمل للسوريين
while supporting Jordan's national development strategy.
من خلال دعم استراتيجية التنمية الوطنية الأردنية .
The idea is for an economic zone,
والفكرة هي لمنطقة اقتصادية،
one in which we could potentially integrate the employment of refugees
والتي نستطيع بقوة من خلالها من دمج اللاجئين في العمل
alongside the employment of Jordanian host nationals.
جنبا إلى جنب مع توظيف المواطنين المضيفين الأردنيين.
And just 15 minutes away from the Zaatari refugee camp,
و على بعد 15 دقيقة فقط من مخيم الزعتري،
home to 83,000 refugees,
هنالك موطن ل 83،000 لاجئ،
is an existing economic zone
وهي المنطقة الاقتصادية الحالية
called the King Hussein Bin Talal Development Area.
والتي تدعى منظقة الملك حسين بن طلال للتنمية
The government has spent over a hundred million dollars
أنفقت الحكومة أكثر من مئة مليون دولار
connecting it to the electricity grid, connecting it to the road network,
لتوصيلها بشبكة الكهرباء والطرق ،
but it lacked two things:
لكنها تفتقر إلى أمرين:
access to labor and inward investment.
الوصول الى العمل والاستثمار الداخلي.
So what if refugees were able to work there
فماذا لو أن اللاجئين كانوا قادرين على العمل هناك
rather than being stuck in camps,
فبدلاً من أن يكونوا عالقين بالمخيمات ،
able to support their families and develop skills through vocational training
سيكونوا قادرين على إعالة أسرهم وتطوير المهارات من خلال التدريب المهني
before they go back to Syria?
قبل أن يعودوا إلى سوريا؟
We recognized that that could benefit Jordan,
نحن ندرك أن الأردن يمكنها الاستفادة من ذلك ،
whose development strategy requires it to make the leap
والتي تتطلب استراتيجيتها التنموية احداث نقلة وقفزة نوعية
as a middle income country to manufacturing.
من دولة ذات دخل متوسط إلى دولة مصنعة ،
It could benefit refugees, but it could also contribute
يمكن أن تفيد اللاجئين، ولكن يمكن أيضا أن تسهم
to the postconflict reconstruction of Syria
في إعادة إعمار سوريا بعد انتهاء الصراع
by recognizing that we need to incubate refugees
من خلال الاعتراف بأننا نحتاج لاحتضان اللاجئين
as the best source of eventually rebuilding Syria.
كأفضل مصدرفي نهاية المطاف لإعادة بناء سوريا
We published the idea in the journal Foreign Affairs.
نشرنا الفكرة في مجلة الشؤون الخارجية.
King Abdullah has picked up on the idea.
الملك عبدالله التقط هذه الفكرة ،
It was announced at the London Syria Conference two weeks ago,
وأعلن عنها في لندن في مؤتمر سوريا قبل أسبوعين،
and a pilot will begin in the summer.
وسيبدأ تطبيقها في الصيف المقبل .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
The third idea that I want to put to you
الفكرة الثالثة التي أريد أن أضعها بين ايديكم
is preference matching between states and refugees
التفضيل المتجانس بين الدول والاجئين
to lead to the kinds of happy outcomes you see here in the selfie
للوصول الى نتائج سعيدة كالتي ترونها هنا في الصور الشخصية
featuring Angela Merkel and a Syrian refugee.
التي تضم أنجيلا ميركل ولاجئين سوريين.
What we rarely do is ask refugees what they want, where they want to go,
ما كنا نادرا ما تفعله هو أن نسأل اللاجئين ما يريدونه، والى اين يريدون الذهاب ،
but I'd argue we can do that
ولكن ما يهمني قوله أنه بامكاننا فعل ذلك
and still make everyone better off.
وأن نجعل كل شخص أفضل حالاً .
The economist Alvin Roth has developed the idea of matching markets,
الخبير الاقتصادي ألفين روث طور فكرة الأسواق المتجانسة ،
ways in which the preference ranking of the parties shapes an eventual match.
بطرق بحيث أن ترتيب الأفضلية للأطراف تشكل تجانس نهائي .
My colleagues Will Jones and Alex Teytelboym
زملائي ويل جونز وأليكس تيتلبويم
have explored ways in which that idea could be applied to refugees,
ابتكروا طرقاً لتطبيق تلك الفكرة على اللاجئين
to ask refugees to rank their preferred destinations,
من خلال سؤال اللاجئين عن الأماكن المفضلة لديهم
but also allow states to rank the types of refugees they want
ولكنها تسمح ايضاً للدول بتصنيف أنواع اللاجئين الذين يرغبون باستضافتهم
on skills criteria or language criteria
بناءاً على معايير المهارات أو معايير اللغة
and allow those to match.
والسماح لهم بالانخراط .
Now, of course you'd need to build in quotas
الآن، وبطبيعة الحال كنت بحاجة الى بناء الحصص
on things like diversity and vulnerability,
مثل التنوع وقابلية التعرض للخطر
but it's a way of increasing the possibilities of matching.
لكنها الوسيلة لزيادة امكانية الاندماج
The matching idea has been successfully used
فكرة الاندماج استخدمت بنجاح
to match, for instance, students with university places,
ومثال ذلك انخراط الطلاب بالجامعات ،
to match kidney donors with patients,
وانخراط المتبرعين بالكلى بالمرضى ،
and it underlies the kind of algorithms that exist on dating websites.
وتكمن خلف الخوارزميات الموجودة على مواقع التعارف .
So why not apply that to give refugees greater choice?
فلماذا لا نطبق فكرة إعطاء اللاجئين خيارات أكبر؟
It could also be used at the national level,
ويمكن أيضا أن تستخدم على المستوى الوطني،.
where one of the great challenges we face
حيث أن واحدة من التحديات الكبيرة التي نواجهها
is to persuade local communities to accept refugees.
هو اقناع المجتمعات المحلية بقبول اللاجئين ،
And at the moment, in my country, for instance,
وفي الوقت الراهن، في بلدي، على سبيل المثال،
we often send engineers to rural areas and farmers to the cities,
نحن غالبا ما نرسل مهندسين للمناطق الريفية والمزارعين إلى المدن،
which makes no sense at all.
وهذا لامعنى له على الإطلاق.
So matching markets offer a potential way to bring those preferences together
لذا فإن تجانس الأسواق توفر وسيلة محتملة لتحقيق تلك التفضيلات معاً
and listen to the needs and demands of the populations that host
والاستماع إلى احتياجات ومطالب من السكان المستظيفين
and the refugees themselves.
واللاجئين نفسهم .
The fourth idea I want to put to you is of humanitarian visas.
الفكرة الرابعة التي أريد أن أضعها بين يديكم هي التأشيرات الإنسانية.
Much of the tragedy and chaos we've seen in Europe
الكثير من المآسي والفوضى التي رأيناها في أوروبا
was entirely avoidable.
كان يمكن تجنبها تماماً ،
It stems from a fundamental contradiction in Europe's asylum policy,
انها تنطلق من التناقض الجوهري في سياسة اللجوء في أوروبا،
which is the following:
وهو ما يلي:
that in order to seek asylum in Europe,
من أجل الحصول على اللجوء في أوروبا،
you have to arrive spontaneously by embarking on those dangerous journeys
فعليك القدوم بشكل عفوي من خلال تلك الرحلات المحفوفة بالمخاطر
that I described.
التي قمت بوصفها .
But why should those journeys be necessary in an era of the budget airline
ولكن لماذا يجب أن تكون مثل هذه الرحلات الخطرة ضرورية ونحن في عصرشركات الطيران الاقتصادية
and modern consular capabilities?
وقدرات السفارات الحديثة ؟
They're completely unnecessary journeys,
انها رحلات غير ضرورية على الإطلاق ،
and last year, they led to the deaths of over 3,000 people
وقد أدت في العام الماضي، إلى وفاة أكثر من 3000 شخص
on Europe's borders and within European territory.
على حدود أوروبا وداخل الأراضي الأوروبية.
If refugees were simply allowed
إذا تم السماح للاجئين ببساطة
to travel directly and seek asylum in Europe,
بالسفر مباشرة وطلب اللجوء في أوروبا،
we would avoid that,
سنتجنب ذلك ،
and there's a way of doing that
وهناك طريقة للقيام بذلك
through something called a humanitarian visa,
من خلال شيء يسمى التأشيرة الإنسانية،
that allows people to collect a visa at an embassy
والتي تتيح للناس للحصول على تأشيرة في سفارة
or a consulate in a neighboring country
أو قنصلية بلد مجاور
and then simply pay their own way
حيث يقومون ببساطة بدفع ثمن رحلتهم
through a ferry or a flight to Europe.
من خلال السفن أو الطيران إلى أوروبا.
It costs around a thousand euros
حوالي ألف 1000 يورو هي التكلفة
to take a smuggler from Turkey to the Greek islands.
لتهريب لاجيء من تركيا إلى الجزر اليونانية.
It costs 200 euros to take a budget airline from Bodrum to Frankfurt.
في حين تكلف 200 يورو للسفر بالطيران الاقتصادي من بودروم الى فرانكفورت.
If we allowed refugees to do that, it would have major advantages.
إذا سمحنا للاجئين بالقيام بهذا فسيكون لذلك ايجابيات كبيرة
It would save lives,
ستنقذ الأرواح
it would undercut the entire market for smugglers,
وسنقطع الطريق على سوق التهريب بشكل كامل
and it would remove the chaos we see from Europe's front line
و ستزيل الفوضى التي نراها في خط الجبهه الأمامية لأوروبا
in areas like the Greek islands.
في مناطق مثل الجزر اليونانية.
It's politics that prevents us doing that rather than a rational solution.
انها السياسة التي تمنعا من القيام بذلك بدلا من حل عقلاني ،
And this is an idea that has been applied.
وهذه الفكرة تم تطبيقها ،
Brazil has adopted a pioneering approach
فقد اعتمدت البرازيل على طريقة رائدة
where over 2,000 Syrians have been able to get humanitarian visas,
حيث أن اكثر من 2000 سوري تمكنوا من الحصول على تأشيرات إنسانية،
enter Brazil, and claim refugee status on arrival in Brazil.
وعندما يدخلون البرازيل يحصلون على وصف لاجيء
And in that scheme, every Syrian who has gone through it
كل سوري بذلك المشروع
has received refugee status and been recognized as a genuine refugee.
يتمتع بوضع اللاجئين وتم الاعتراف به كلاجئ حقيقي.
There is a historical precedent for it as well.
وهناك سابقة تاريخية أخرى كذلك ،
Between 1922 and 1942,
فبين عامي 1922 و 1942،
these Nansen passports were used as travel documents
جوازات السفرهذه استخدمت كوثائق للسفر
to allow 450,000 Assyrians, Turks and Chechens
للسماح بنقل 45,000 من الأرمن والشيشان والأتراك
to travel across Europe
للسفر عبر أوروبا
and claim refugee status elsewhere in Europe.
والحصول على وصفة لاجئ في أماكن أخرى في أوروبا.
And the Nansen International Refugee Office
والمكتب الدولي للاجئين
received the Nobel Peace Prize
حصل على جائزة نوبل للسلام
in recognition of this being a viable strategy.
تقديراً لهذ الاسترتيجية القابلة للتطبيق.
So all four of these ideas that I've presented you
لذلك كل الأفكار الأربع التي قدمتها لكم
are ways in which we can expand Amira's choice set.
هي طريق يمكننا من خلالها توسيع نطاق خيارات أميرة ،
They're ways in which we can have greater choice for refugees
إنها طرق يمكننا من خلالها الحصول على خيارات عظيمة تخص اللاجئين
beyond those basic, impossible three options
بعيداً عن الخيارات الثلاثة الأساسية المستحيلة
I explained to you
لقد شرحت لكم
and still leave others better off.
حتى تترك الآخرين أفضل حالاً.
In conclusion, we really need a new vision,
فى الختام، نحن حقاً بحاجة إلى رؤية جديدة،
a vision that enlarges the choices of refugees
رؤية توسع خيارات اللاجئين
but recognizes that they don't have to be a burden.
ولكنها تدرك أنهم لا يجب أن يكونوا عبئاً.
There's nothing inevitable about refugees being a cost.
لا يوجد شيء لا مفر منه حول تكلفة اللاجئين .
Yes, they are a humanitarian responsibility,
نعم، هي قضية إنسانية ومسؤولية،
but they're human beings with skills, talents, aspirations,
ولكنهم بشر يمتلكون مهارات ومواهب وطموحات،
with the ability to make contributions -- if we let them.
ولديهم القدرة على المساهمة ... إذا سمحنا لهم بذلك .
In the new world,
في العالم الجديد،
migration is not going to go away.
الهجرة ليست في طريقها إلى الزوال.
What we've seen in Europe will be with us for many years.
ما رأيناه في أوروبا سيكون حاضراً معنا لسنوات عديدة.
People will continue to travel,
الناس سيستمرون في السفر،
they'll continue to be displaced,
وسيستمرون في التشرد عن أوطانهم ،
and we need to find rational, realistic ways of managing this --
لذا نحن بحاجة لإيجاد طريقة واقعية وعقلانية لإدارة هذا الأمر ...
not based on the old logics of humanitarian assistance,
لا تستند على المنطق القديم في المساعدة الإنسانية،
not based on logics of charity,
ولا تستند على منطق الأعمال الخيرية ،
but building on the opportunities
ولكن تستند على بناء الفرص
offered by globalization, markets and mobility.
التي يتيحها التنقل والأسواق المعولمة ،
I'd urge you all to wake up and urge our politicians
أؤكد لكم أنه يجب علينا الاستيقاظ من غفلتنا وأن نحث السياسين
to wake up to this challenge.
على أن يستيقظوا ليواجهوا هذا التحدي .
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )